Soccer was my reason for living.
サッカーは私の全てでした
I always dreamed of becoming
a professional soccer player.
プロのサッカー選手になることを
夢見ていました
I thought that happiness came from fame,
スター選手になって
a good career,
大金を稼げば
幸せになれると考えていました
money.
両親は私が6歳の時に
When I was six,
my parents signed me up for soccer.
サッカーチームに入れてくれました
私はサッカーに熱中していました
I really loved playing soccer.
I spent all my time at the stadium,
even late into the night.
朝から晩までグラウンドで
過ごしていました
12歳の時 母からエホバに
ついて教わりました
When I was 12,
I learned about Jehovah from my mom.
At that time,
母は聖書を学び始めていました
she started studying the Bible.
And after about a year,
1年ほどして 私は伝道を始めました
I began to preach from door to door.
17歳になって 学校を卒業し
When I was 17 years old,
I finished school
and I received an invitation
from the Dynamo Soccer Club in Kiev.
キエフのディナモ･サッカー･クラブに
入団しました
Oh, that was unforgettable!
その時のことは忘れられません
Yes, my emotions were running high
子供のころからディナモでプレー
することを夢見ていたので
because since childhood
I had always dreamed of playing for Dynamo.
とても興奮しました
From that moment on,
all my energy and all my time
その時からエネルギーと時間を
全てサッカーに捧げました
were devoted to my career.
毎日トレーニングと試合に
明け暮れていました
Every day we either trained or there was a game.
There was no time left for spiritual things.
エホバを崇拝するための
時間はありませんでした
当たり前なんですが
Of course, being around people like that,
I became just like them.
チームメートの強い影響を受けました
大金を稼いで何でもできる
ようになったため
I led an immoral lifestyle
because huge amounts of money
opened up many opportunities.
不道徳な生き方をするようになりました
Going to nightclubs, the nightlife
ナイトクラブに行って遊びましたが
—it was so immoral.
とても不道徳な場所でした
みんなが私に会おうとし
Everyone wants to be
your friend and to meet you.
友達になりたがりました
And, of course, this was tempting.
大きな誘惑になりました
たくさんのお金を不動産に投資しました
I also invested huge sums
of money in real estate.
I wanted to create a foundation
for the future and wealth for myself,
将来に備えて自分や家族や
親戚が困らないように
my family, and my relatives
so that no one would be in need.
財産をためておきたかったんです
それが幸せな生活だと
本気で思っていました
Yes, I was sure that this really was happiness.
そういう生活を9年ほど続けました
This continued for nine years.
The turning point
ある問題で経営者側と話し合った時に
was a conversation with management
when an issue came up,
全てが変わりました
and they hurled insults at me.
私は何度も侮辱され
At that moment, I felt worthless,
使い捨てのカップのように
扱われていると感じました
like a disposable cup
that you use and then crush
用が済んだらつぶされて
捨てられるんです
and throw away.
Besides, a new generation
of soccer players was arriving
その後チームの若返りが図られ
—many young guys.
私はスターティングメンバーから
外されました
I stopped being included in the starting lineup.
さらに 景気が非常に悪くなり
Also, the financial crisis began,
不動産の価値が暴落しました
and real estate prices fell drastically.
私は混乱し どうしたらいいか
分からなくなりました
I panicked; I didn’t know what to do.
And I started to think about the meaning of life:
それで人生の意味について
考えるようになりました
‘What really is the meaning of life?
‘If it’s not a career, not money
「キャリアやお金に意味がないとしたら
—then what is it?’
人生っていったい何なんだ」
と思いました
And then I remembered everything that I learned
その時 10代の頃に学んだ
about Jehovah when I was a teenager.
エホバのことを思い出しました
I began to study
the Bible again along with my wife.
そして妻と共に聖書を学び始めました
After a year, I started preaching again,
and in 2009,
1年後には再び伝道を始め
2009年にバプテスマを受けて
エホバの証人になりました
I was baptized as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
大きな喜びと満足感を味わいました
And this brought me so much joy and satisfaction.
メダルや優勝カップを獲得した時の
気持ちとは比べものになりません
These feelings can’t be compared
to winning any medal or cup.
I realized that I couldn’t slave for two masters,
2人の主人の奴隷になれないことは
分かっていましたが
ディナモ・キエフでさらに2年間
プレーしなければなりませんでした
but I still had to play
two more years for Dynamo Kyiv.
Although it was a difficult time,
いろいろと大変でしたが
その状況を活用して
I took advantage of this opportunity,
エホバについて知らせる
ことができました
and I am thankful to Jehovah that a good witness
エホバに感謝しています
was given about his name.
There were some soccer players
何人かの選手は真理に興味を示しました
who showed interest in the truth.
In 2011 when my contract ended,
2011年に契約が終了し
プロ選手としてのキャリアは
終わりました
I finished my professional career.
First Timothy chapter 6
テモテ第一 6章は
encourages us “to place [our] hope,
not on uncertain riches,
「不確かな富にではなく
神に希望を抱［き］」
「立派な行いに励［む］」
よう勧めています
but on God,” and “to be rich in fine works.”
時折 「後悔していませんか」とか
People ask me: “Do you regret it?”
“Maybe you’d like to come back;
do you miss soccer?”
「またプレーしたくありませんか」
などと尋ねられることがあります
And I honestly and sincerely say no.
私は心から「いいえ」と答えます
I don’t miss it, and I don’t want to go back
サッカーをやめたことを
全く後悔していません
because my relationship with Jehovah—
エホバとの関係の方が
ずっと大切だからです
Well, it can’t be compared to anything.
これは何物にも代えられません
Everything that this world offers is all short-lived,
この世界が提供するものは
一時的ではかないものです
and it’s only an illusion.
People see only one side of the picture
—the fame and the money.
人々は名声とお金という
きらびやかな面しか見ていませんが
The other side are
the injuries and disappointments.
実際には傷つき
落胆することばかりです
It’s very hard psychologically and emotionally;
精神的にも感情的にも楽ではなく
you have no freedom.
自由もありません
That’s why it’s better
to give the very best to the One
努力を評価してくれるエホバのために
ベストを尽くすのは素晴らしいことです
who appreciates it.
What you do for Jehovah
will always bring you happiness,
そうすれば必ず幸福感 喜び
joy, and satisfaction.
満足感を味わうことができます